本格的な夏の日差しが
肌を焦がしていく様に
私もあなたに恋焦がれる
海へドライブ 運転するよ
横顔撫でる 潮風が気持ちいいsummer day
la la la summer day
ビーチパラソルカラフルだ yeah
砂浜に咲く　花みたい
KISS YOU あなたの心
もっともっと近くにいたい　感じたい
私だけ見て
KISS YOU ぐっと膨らんだ
胸の思い　唇にのせて　伝えたいと
だから　KISS YOU
だから　さあ　KISS YOU
Episode 10
Hachiken
Says Goodbye to Pork Bowl
Hey! Don't be so greedy!
おい　そんなにがっつくなって
Fine, fine!
分かった　分かった　後でやるから
You'll get more later!
八軒ってさ　頭いいけどバカだよね
Hachiken, you're smart, but stupid.
えっ？
Huh?
だってさ　何かというと面倒事引き受けてんじゃん
You're always taking on stuff
that's a pain in the butt,
ピザ会やら豚丼のことやらさ
like the pizza party and Pork Bowl.
The rest of us never really thought
私ら　殺して食べることって今まで深く考えたことなかったんだよね
a whole lot about killing
and eating them, you know.
当たり前過ぎて
It was something we took for granted.
だけど　あんたはそういうの考え込んでのたうち回ってんじゃん？
But you're flailing around
thinking about it.
バカ正直に
Just being brutally honest.
でも　だんだんバカにできなくなってきたっていうか
But it's become harder for
me to make fun of you.
当たり前だと思い込んでたものを
Maybe it's important to reconsider
things you've always taken for granted.
もう一度捉え直すのも大切なのかなって
Whoa!
あたぁ…こぶできちゃったぁ
Ow...
I'm gonna have a bump soon...
大丈夫かよ
You okay?
あー　もう　八軒がかわいがるから
Man...
It's because you spoil him
that he's so friendly.
こんなに人懐っこくなっちゃって
If I can't eat pork anymore,
what are you gonna do?
豚食べられなくなったらどーすんのよ
You'd better take responsibility!
責任取ってよね
Uh, sure.
はいはい
ちゃんと分かってんの
Do you really get it?!
もう
Man, I'm soaked.
すっげえ汗かいた
Huh? What's wrong?
どうした
俺　話聞いちゃったんだけど
I overheard you guys...
何の？
Yeah?
豚舎で吉野と…
At the pig pen. You and Yoshino.
"What're you gonna do?"
お前どうすんの　責任取るの
"You gonna take responsibility?"
あー　あの話か
Oh, that?
あいつのことは真剣に考えてる
I'm completely serious about it!
けじめはつけるさ
I'll take responsibility!
八軒は大人になったんだな
Hachiken, you're all grown up...
Uh, sure.
まあな　お疲れ
Later!
Good job.
お疲れー
What's the matter, Tokiwa?
どうした　常盤
誰にも言うなよ
Don't tell anyone...
...but Hachiken and Yoshino...
八軒と吉野が…
Dairy Science
えぇぇ！？
What?!
Shh!
しー　誰にも言うなよ　ここだけの話だぞ
Don't tell anyone!
It doesn't leave this room!
ということは　えー　ここで著者が言ってるのは
So, uh, what the author's
trying to say here is...
情緒を解する人というのは
People with deep empathy
花の盛りだけに感動するんじゃないってことになった
are not only struck by wonder
when flowers are in full bloom.
花が咲く前にわくわくするとか
They experience joy when flowers
are about to bloom,
咲き終わって萎れる…
and also melancholy when
flowers wilt and fade away.
何か変な空気だな
Something feels strange...
Campus Motto
Defy Logic  Cooperation  Diligence
Hachiken, Yoshino, come to
the guidance counselor's office.
八軒　吉野　ちょっと進路指導室に来なさい
はい
Okay.
何だろ
What's this about?
Guidance Counseling Office
不純異性交遊！？
Improper sexual relations?!
俺と！？
Me?
私が！？
With him?!
ああ　そういう噂が
Yes. That's the rumor.
まあ　発情…もとい春機発動期だから
Well, you are going through heat...
I mean puberty, so I can sympathize.
分からんでもないが
思春期って言ってください
Please say "adolescence" instead!
つーかないっす
Wait, we're not!
今の生活のどこに異性と交遊する暇があるんすか
When would we even have the time to hook up
with the way our lives are right now, anyway?!
土日も部活だし
We have club activities
on the weekends, too!
じゃあ　噂のようなことは…
Then the rumors are...
Totally unfounded!
ありません！
I see.
そうか　じゃあ　よし
Well, good.
そもそも何でそんなデマが飛び交ってんですか
Why are rumors like that
flying around, anyway?!
さあな
Who knows...
押すなってば
Who was it?
誰だ
Yay!
イエイ
But at the pig pen, you guys were...
だってお前たち豚舎で…
今日も元気に強制労働　イエイ　イエイ
Just another cheerful day
of forced labor! Yeah!
Oh, Hachiken's popular
with the pigs, as usual.
おっ　相変わらず豚にモテモテだな　八軒
お～う…
Hey—
できちゃった
I'm gonna have a bump soon...
責任取ってよね
You'd better take responsibility!
あれか
Oh, that?
We were talking about pigs!
豚の話だよ
えっ？　八軒　豚の雌とできてんの？
Huh? You got a pig girlfriend?
I think you can punch Tokiwa.
八軒は常盤殴っていいと思うよ
強制労働もうすぐ終わりだったのに
And I was almost done
with forced labor...
Three extra days aren't enough!
３日追加でも生ぬるい
They're really noisy today.
今日はずいぶんうるさいなぁ
餌箱ぴかぴかだね
The feedbox is squeaky clean.
Maybe they didn't get fed.
もらってないのかな
今日は餌やらなくていいぞ
You don't need to feed them today.
Huh?
えっ？　何でですか？
Why's that?
あした出荷する段取りができた
We've made arrangements to
send them off tomorrow.
解体するとき清潔に保たれるよう
We purge their digestive system
in order to maintain hygiene
胃腸の中を空にしておく
when they are being processed.
いよいよお別れか
It's finally time to say goodbye...
ごめんね　おなかすかしてるよね
Sorry, you guys must be hungry.
俺…俺　買います
I...
I'll buy him.
What?
先生　豚って…１頭幾らするんですか
Sensei, how much does a pig cost?
Pigs this size would fetch
この大きさだと　家畜市場で３万といったところか
around thirty thousand yen
at the livestock market.
買ってどうする
What would you do with it?
ペットのようにかわいがり続けるのか
Will you keep taking
care of it as a pet?
場所は？　餌代は？
Where would you keep it?
What about its feed?
お前が卒業したら　その豚は誰が引き継ぐ？
Who will take care of
it after you graduate?
買うっていっても　生きてる豚丼じゃないです
I didn't say I'd buy Pork Bowl alive.
肉になった豚丼を買います
I'll buy Pork Bowl as meat!
What? Meat?
えっ　肉って…
How many kilos would that be?
何ｋｇあるんだ？
金はあるのか
You have the money?
あります　夏休みバイトした分が
I do!
I have money from my summer job!
うむ　売った
Very well. Sold!
Ooezo Agricultural High School Dormitory for Future Agriculture Managers
ごめんな　おなかすいたよな
Sorry.
You guys must be hungry.
All right, time to switch.
よし　じゃあ　交代な
こら　豚丼　また後でやってやるから　ったく
Hey, Pork Bowl.
I'll brush you again later.
Jeez.
重っ
So heavy...
短いよな　お前たちの命
Your lives are so short...
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven...
１　２　３　４　５　６　７…
Eight!
８頭　これで最後だな
That's the last of them.
あ…あの
U-Um...
何だい
Yeah?
えーと…　その…
Um, well...
よろしくお願いします
Please take good care of them.
Please separate out the meat from
the pig marked with an "X."
×印の付いた豚の肉は別口でお願いします
はい　了解しましたよ
Okay, got it.
八軒　あの豚が肉になって戻ってきたら　知らせる
Hachiken,
I'll let you know when
its meat comes back in.
はい
Okay.
へえー　自腹で買ったんか
Huh, so you bought him, yourself?
豚丼　いつ戻ってくんだ？
When's Pork Bowl coming back?
熟成期間あるから　３日くらいじゃね？
There's an aging period,
so maybe in about three days?
なあ？
Right?
Yeah...
Isn't meat better fresh?
肉って新鮮な方がうまいんじゃねえのか
腐りかけがうまいっていうべ
They say it's better
when it's half-rotten.
アミノ酸だろ？
It's about amino acids, right?
先生　豚肉の熟成って…
Sensei, how is pork aged?
Hm?
All right!
よし　いっちょ説明するか
Chemistry II
Allow me to explain!
Carboxyl Group
Amine Group
Amino Acid
D-Amino Acid
タンパク質に本来味はない
Protein does not have
any flavor by itself.
が　酵素の働きで分解されて
But when it's broken down by enzymes,
アミノ酸とペプチドが増加する
the amount of amino acids and
peptides in the meat increases.
いわゆる　うま味成分ってやつだな
They're what you call flavor compounds.
That's how meat aging works.
これが熟成の仕組みだ
さばいた肉を２℃から４℃で保存
The processed meat is kept at
two to four degrees Celsius.
For pork, three to five days
is considered optimal.
豚だと３日から５日がベストだそうだ
育てるときに工夫できることって何かあるんですか
Are there any techniques to use
during their growth period?
Yeah. Recently, whey-fed
pigs have become popular.
うん　最近注目されてるのがホエー豚だ
牛乳から脂肪分などのチーズ成分を取り除いた液体をホエーという
Whey is the liquid that remains after
cheese curds are removed from milk.
It's produced in great quantities
during the manufacture of cheese.
チーズを作る過程で大量に出るので
昔は捨てられていたものだ
In the past, it was a waste product.
Huh?
ありゃ　まだ化学の授業中か
これを与えて飼育したのはホエー豚
Pigs that are given such a diet
are called whey-fed pigs.
Are you guys still in chemistry class?
あー　八軒君が実習の豚肉１頭分買っちゃって…
Oh, Hachiken-kun bought pork made
from one of the practicum animals.
They have tender, flavorful meat
marketed as branded meat.
Whey has high nutritional value, so it's a
hot research topic for meat manufacturers.
丸々１頭分か
One whole pig?
ほう　あいつ変わったことするな
Huh, he sure does unusual things.
Hmm...
Okay, in today's livestock
science class,
えー　今日の畜産の授業は視聴覚室で映像を見ます
we'll watch a video in
the multimedia room.
と畜場の映像です
It's about the slaughterhouse.
家畜がと畜場に運ばれていくところから
It shows the entire process, from the livestock
being taken to the slaughterhouse
枝肉になるところまでが撮影されています
to their carcasses being processed into meat.
生き物の命を奪う映像が入っていますので
It will show life being taken from living things.
こういうのが生理的に駄目な人は無理して見る必要はありません
Anyone who cannot stomach
seeing things like that
will not be forced to to watch.
重ねて言います
I repeat,
no one will be forced to watch.
強制はしません
では見たい人だけ視聴覚室へ移動してください
Okay, those of you who want to watch
this should go to the multimedia room.
どうする
I think it'll be a little
too much for me...
俺　きつい　ちょっと
Okay!
よし
The animals in holding pens are
washed down to remove dirt.
係留場で待機させられていた家畜の汚れをシャワーで落とす
次に１頭ずつ場内に送り出す
Then, they're sent one by one
into the slaughter area.
They're stunned using carbon
dioxide gas or an electric shock,
ガス　電気などを使って仮死状態にする
心臓が動いていないと
because if the heart stops,
bloodletting will be incomplete,
この後の血抜きに失敗し　腐りやすい
resulting in poor-quality
meat susceptible to degradation.
まずい肉になってしまうからだ
Next...
次に…
What'd you think?
どうだった
Well, I knew about it,
but it was still eye-opening.
いやぁ　分かっちゃいたけど…
Aikawa...
相川
Well, I knew what would happen,
but it still got to me.
いやぁ…予想してたけど結構くるね
大丈夫か
You okay?
これ乗り越えないと獣医なんてとてもなれないしね
If I can't get over this,
there's no hope for me becoming a vet.
Yeah.
あのスピードで畜体をさばけるのは
They could only butcher
the animals so fast
動物の体を知り尽くしてるからこそだ
because they know their
anatomy in and out.
獣医を目指すからには
Since I want to be a vet,
I want to have as much knowledge
and precision as they do!
あのぐらいの知識と正確さが欲しい
Dorm bento boxes are here!
寮弁届いたぞ
What is it today?
今日何
Beef bowl.
牛丼
Ugh.
俺が見に行ったと畜場のおっちゃんは
The guy working at the slaughterhouse I went to
was wearing something that looked like armor.
鎖かたびらみたいの着込んでたぞ
何でも真剣にやるのはカッコイイよな
It's awesome to be serious
about what you do.
内臓抜いたら急に肉って感じになるよね
They suddenly turn into "meat"
once their organs are removed.
Meat and offal.
肉とホルモン
I wonder how many animals
they can process in a day.
１日に何頭さばけるんだろう
八軒は平気だったか
Were you okay, Hachiken?
Oh, yeah...
夏休み鹿解体したから　わりと…
I cleaned a deer over the summer,
so it wasn't too bad...
You still look pale, though.
でもお前顔青いよ
食欲ないならその肉もらっていい？
If you're not hungry,
can I have your meat?
No!
やらん
Hachiken, you here?
八軒いるか
The pork arrived.
It's in the meat processing room.
豚肉　加工室に届いてるぞ
骨を取り除いて　肉の部位に切り分けてもらってある
I had them debone and cut
the meat into parts.
There is 51 kilos of meat here,
from the pig Hachiken bought.
八軒の買った豚の精肉　５１ｋｇ
This is all of it.
これで全部だ
51 kilos...
５１ｋｇ…
女子１人分くらい？
So, like, about as much a girl weighs?
Tokiwa.
常盤ぁ　ちょっと　こっち来なさい
Come over here.
えっ　何？　何？
What, what?
ちっちゃくなっちゃったな
He's so small now...
あの１頭から精肉５１ｋｇが取れた
We got 51 kilos from that one pig.
Right now, the market price
for pork is 496 yen per kilo.
今の豚肉の市場価格が１ｋｇ当たり４９６円
That makes it a total of 25,296 yen.
２万５，２９６円分のお買い上げだな
Did you bring the money?
金は持ってきたのか
あっ　はい
Oh, yes.
Payment
Food Processing Department:
Meat Processing Room
Meat Processing Practicum Room
But, 50 kilos, huh...
しかし　５０ｋｇか
どうすっかな
Wonder what I'll do with it...
あら　まだどうするか決めてなかったの？
Oh, you hadn't decided yet?
加工とか流通とか　よかったら相談に乗るわよ
If you'd like, I can advise you about
processing and distribution options.
マジでか？　悪いな
Really? Thanks.
友達でしょ？　気にしないで
We're friends, right?
Don't worry about it.
If it bothers you, might I have a tiny
bit of that meat as a consulting fee?
どうしても気になるなら
顧問料としてちょびっとだけお肉を頂けるかしら？
ほら　そこの大腰筋でいいわ
There, that psoas major muscle is fine.
えっ　こんな少しでいいのか
Oh, you only want this little piece?
お前　いいやつだな…
You're a good person...
Wait, that's the tenderloin!
大腰筋ってヒレ肉じゃんか
最高級部位
The best cut!
チッ
何するにしても結局食うんだべ？
Either way, you're going
to eat it, right?
Let's see, for pork...
豚料理っつーと
ベーコンとか　ソーセージとか　ハムとか…
You can make bacon, sausage, ham...
豚丼とか
Like a pork bowl?
いや　いや　いや
No, no, no!
話は聞いた
I heard the situation.
Whoa!
ちょちょ…ちょ…ちょっと待ってください
H-H-Hey! Please wait!
あの…　俺　まだ…
Um, I still haven't...
But what're you going to
do with 50 kilos of meat?
んなこと言ったって　この５０ｋｇの肉どーすんだ？
早く決めないとなくなるぞ
If you don't make up your
mind soon, it'll be gone.
Gone?
なくなる？
Girls love you when you have money;
金持ってると女にモテるが
肉持ってると男にモテちゃうからな
guys love you when you have meat.
Hey, jump!
おら　跳んでみろよ
こいつやっぱり肉持ってやがったぜ
End of the
Century
I knew he had meat!
Wait!
待てぃ
豚丼！
Hup!
Pork Bowl!
豚丼！
I'll become targeted by a meat hunt!
肉狩りに遭ってしまう
Please teach me how to make bacon!
ベーコンの作り方教えてください
いいよ
Sure.
加工室の使用許可は？
Do you have permission to
use the processing room?
もらいました
I do!
You have 50 kilos, right?
５０ｋｇだっけ　何人で作業する？
How many people are
going to work on it?
Just myself!
１人で！
Meat Processing Practicum Room
Formerly Known As: Milk Processing Practicum Room (Livestock Practicum Room)
Okay, done.
よし　終わりました
うん　じゃあ　次はこいつを擦り込んでいく
Next, rub this into the meat.
What is it?
それは？
塩やらスパイスやらを混ぜたもんだ
It's a mix of salt and spices.
Because of the amount you're working
with,  it'll take a while.
こんだけの量になると結構かかるぞ
Okay.
はい
Oh, you can keep them on.
いや　したままでいいぞ
素手でやらせてください
I'd like to use my bare hands.
'Kay!
よし　下ごしらえ終わったー
Prepwork, done!
お疲れ　後は薫製の日まで１週間冷蔵庫に入れて熟成だ
Good job!
Now you let it cure for a week
in the fridge until it's time to smoke it.
My hands sting...
手ひりひり　手首痛え
My wrists hurt.
結構重労働だろ
Pretty intensive work, right?
素人が５０ｋｇの肉を全部１人で下ごしらえするとか　あり得んぞ
It's unreal for an amateur
to prep 50 kilos of meat by himself.
ですよね
You're right...
Partway through, I wondered
what I'd gotten myself into.
途中から　俺何やってんだって…
でも　何か…
But I kind of...
少しすっきりしました
feel a little better now.
When the bacon's done,
can I buy some off you?
ベーコンできたら　少し買わせてもらっていいか
What?
えっ？　いいっす　お金なんて
You don't need to pay me!
八軒が買った肉だろ
But you bought the meat, right?
金払うよ
I'll pay.
労働の代価はきちんと払わないと多摩子に怒られるからな
Tamako will get mad at me
if I don't pay you for the work you put in.
そっか　そっすね
I see. Okay.
じゃ　ありがたく
Thanks, then.
すごい手だね
Your hands are in rough shape.
I wasn't used to it,
慣れない作業したら
切ったりつったり大変だったよ
so my hands got all cut
and cramped and stuff.
鹿解体したときも思ったけど
I thought this when I
cleaned the deer, too,
俺料理人に向いてないわ
but I'm not cut out to be a cook.
でもカッコイイ手だよ
But they're cool hands.
Huh?
ちょっと待ってて
Wait here.
はい　これ
Okay, here.
They're medicated compresses
made from natural ingredients.
天然素材の貼り薬
臭いがきつくないからよかったら使ってみて
They don't have a strong smell,
so feel free to try them out.
ありがとう　御影　愛を感じるぜ
Thanks, Mikage!
I feel your love!
Oh, store-bought compresses stink.
市販の湿布って臭いからな
その臭い　馬が嫌うんだよ
Horses hate the smell.
さっさとその薬使いなさいよ　八軒
Hurry up and put them on, Hachiken.
さすが御影　馬への愛を感じるぜ
Nice, Mikage. I feel your
love for the horses!
Smokehouse
Something smells good.
何かいい匂いがする
Did you start smoking it?
薫製始まったの？
Yeah.
うん　夜には出来上がるって
It should be done tonight.
ってことはまだしばらく薫製する？
So you'll be smoking
it for a while longer?
Yeah.
ちょっと待ってて
Wait here!
ついでにこれもお願い
Can you smoke this, too?
一度スモークチーズ作ってみたかったんだよね
I've always wanted to try my
hand at making smoked cheese!
このチーズどこから持ってきたの？
Where'd you get this cheese?
That's a secret.
ひ　み　つ
Oh, you started smoking it?
薫製始まったのか
お…おう
Y-Yeah!
Smokehouse
It smells really good.
すげえいい匂い
Doesn't it?
だろ
葬式みたいだな
It's like a funeral.
Huh?
いや　何か親父の葬式思い出した
Oh, it's just...
I just remembered my dad's funeral.
I guess this is like a
funeral for Pork Bowl.
確かに豚丼の葬式みたいなもんだよな
Yeah, appreciating the bacon will
be like paying our respects.
おいしく頂くのが供養になる
というわけで早く食わせろ
So, let us eat already.
そんなの人間のエゴだろ
That's just your human ego talking!
If I were Pork Bowl,
俺が豚丼だったら
奇麗に食われようが　汚く食い散らかされようが
I wouldn't care whether people
ate every bit or made a mess!
とにかく嫌だね　恨みまくるね
I'd still hate it!
I'd resent it a lot!
八軒
Hachiken!
Piping hot rice!
炊きたてごは～ん
でも肉が…
But the meat isn't...
八軒
Hachiken!
あー　豚丼の大腰筋
Hey, that's Pork Bowl's tenderloin!
Making bacon out of tenderloin?
大腰筋をベーコンにするなんて
豚丼が浮かばれないじゃない
That'd be an insult to Pork Bowl.
スカイツリー豚丼
Skytree Pork Bowl!
ご飯より肉の量が多い
There's more meat than rice!
That's immoral!
邪道よ
バカヤロー　肉は正義だ
No, idiot!
Meat is justice!
そんじゃ…
Okay, then...
八軒　いただきます
Thanks for the food, Hachiken!
Okay!
Man, bittersweet!
甘じょっぺー
たまには手紙を書いてみようよ
どっかにポストカードでもあったけ
懐かしい顔に見けて
ほんの数行ノスタルジーを
調子はどうですか
忙しくしていますか
無我夢中で探しまわってた
あの夢の具合はどんなだい
気分転換くらいのノリで
一緒に歌わないか
そして無我夢中で探しまわってた
あの夢の続きを語り合おうよ
明日は頑張ろうぜ
今はそこにある未来へ
駆け出して さぁ 行こう
This story is a work of fiction.
The people and groups are fictitious, but the themes relating to food and life are firmly based in reality. Visiting the places and facilities used as models can be dangerous and may result it contracting diseases from the animals. Please enjoy this story as a work of fiction.